[SPEAKER_00]: I have a few more questions from around the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: These two are related.
[SPEAKER_00]: They are in terms of becoming a Sotāpanna, really.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, one friend asks, due to an insight that I had a year ago,
[SPEAKER_00]: I take things less personally.
[SPEAKER_00]: And my aversion is really minimum.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when it happens, it doesn't last long at all.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I can see that I am still liable to aversion.
[SPEAKER_00]: So my practice right now is holding on to that notion of non-self that I saw, and the non-ownership as the general background tone of life, or the larger container of things.
[SPEAKER_00]: How should I proceed?
[SPEAKER_00]: And this person is actually just a lay person who's living at home, very kind of relaxed lifestyle.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: But beyond that, I don't know what they do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, how should I proceed?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's really more of a... Is there anything else I should do?
[SPEAKER_01]: type of thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because what's described is fine, but the question is, why are you asking yourself, how should I proceed?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is what you describe is not enough?
[SPEAKER_01]: Are you aware there is more to be done?
[SPEAKER_01]: Are you not sure about it?
[SPEAKER_01]: If all these questions persist, means you can't say you are beyond doubt, which means you should proceed by doing more of the same and then investigate in what areas you can improve and you might have been lacking.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, maybe you had an insight that freed you from the sense of ownership to a degree, which is possible, you know, even people who don't
[SPEAKER_01]: We don't necessarily commit to the practice 24-7.
[SPEAKER_01]: They could still experience non-ownership and experience release on account of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But is there a cultivation of a suitable basis for that insight to be taken then even further?
[SPEAKER_01]: Such as, is there a sufficient virtue?
[SPEAKER_01]: Accomplishment in virtue, sense restraint, seeing the signs of your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: All those prerequisites, basically, for a Sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_01]: People don't have the right view, not because, you know, dhamma is some secret mystery that they still haven't figured out.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's because the things that they read and the things that they understand do not pertain deeply enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they don't pertain deeply enough not because of the lack of information or lack of their intelligence to understand.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's because of the lack of the sufficient basis of that morality, virtue, accomplishment, solitude, sign of the mind, guarding of the sense doors.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if that basis is thoroughly developed, very little instruction will be necessary to understand the not-self.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, cultivate it further.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like that idea of not-self.
[SPEAKER_00]: A person can get that idea, that theory, but it remains a theory until you actually live in accordance with that idea.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, and even as a theory, as I said, it can have a, you know, it can be theoretical to some degree, but it has its practical side of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that practicality is something you don't want to...
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't want to be sort of living off of it, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you had some like a practical release, fine, now have thousand more of those.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not about having one.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, the Buddha said to even the actual sotāpānas, actual sakadāgāmīs, actual anāgāmīs, he said, did you understand the dhamma for the sake of cherishing that view that you have, or for the sake of abandoning even that through your repetitive work and diligence until you have crossed the shore?
[SPEAKER_01]: And it says, no, it's for understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, keep digging.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't stop, because you're anāgāmī now, or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Keep digging, and don't carry that raft with you when you cross the shore.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's for that purpose.
[SPEAKER_00]: Continue that renunciation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you have it, if you've had any kind of insight of any kind, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, a thousand times more, repeat the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, when you do, just keep doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And keep increasing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you'll know when to stop.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like that you get the the right idea, but then you need to... it needs to root itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, you bring it into reality, you bring it into realization.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to cultivate it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You might plant the best seeds, but unless you look after and clear the weeds and then protect it from becoming too dry or too wet, they're not gonna germinate properly or they will not be as good.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to attend to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to keep doing it and keep an eye on it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what do I do next?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's more like, how do I do more of this?
[SPEAKER_01]: Even increase the quality of what I've been doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's... how to do more of that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Those instructions are already there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: How do I do more of this?
[SPEAKER_01]: Means I already know how I've done this.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, now just do more of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not a secret.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's more like on the level of diligence, work, repetition and sticking to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And yes, not living off on the that kind of...
[SPEAKER_01]: I had this experience a year ago.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was part... Nobody denies that people have experiences.
[SPEAKER_01]: What you deny, what I deny, is basically the view that you can just now assume it's finished or something because you saw it once.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but I had experience it was real.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you also had experience of suffering millions of times and it was equally real.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, which is more now?
[SPEAKER_01]: Your one experience of release or every single time you still suffer?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there you go.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's your answer.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you still suffer?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Keep then regenerating, cultivating that experience in ourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it's not clear, clarify it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's your work.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it's clear, then sustain it in its clarity.
[SPEAKER_01]: Protect it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And make sure the virtue is there to match, to sustain that basis.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sense restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't become careless and keep doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you keep clarifying, polishing that view.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Realization, realization, bringing it, you're bringing it into reality, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah, sure, sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Making it more real.
[SPEAKER_01]: Literal meaning, yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like an insight, but then you just... Well, that's what bhāvanā is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Keeping it alive, bhāvanā, keeping it in the being, bringing it into the actuality, the being of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sustaining it in its existence, whatever you are cultivating.
[SPEAKER_00]: Until it takes...
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you'll know, as I said, when to stop.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't stop by decision to stop.
[SPEAKER_01]: You stop when there's no more work to be done.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you don't need to decide that.
[SPEAKER_01]: That just happens.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the other question from another friend, he or she says,
[SPEAKER_00]: I've reached a point where I can clearly see arising feelings and thoughts as not mine and simply just as a risen phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_00]: But sometimes I lapse in mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: I lose the correct perspective and suffer as a result.
[SPEAKER_00]: Also, I think every time a feeling comes up, there is a self bundled with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It takes about a second for me to realize it's anicca, dukkha, anatta.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's too long.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I'm wondering, if I've reached the Sotāpanna stage, if I haven't, how far do I have to go?
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, if you're wondering whether you have reached it, you haven't.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, if you need somebody else to answer it, means you don't know it for yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like you just said, once you finish the work, you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not, it's not gonna, it's not like, oh, I can stop now because I'm a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's more like, no, it's because I'm a sotāpanna, I just, the work cannot happen anymore, because there's no more work, to that extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, you keep looking for work, and there is no more work, and then you calm down, and then you realize there is no more work.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how suttas always describe it as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: He works diligently.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like, oh, is this handle worn out yet?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: He just uses the handle.
[SPEAKER_01]: He uses it until he realizes it's worn out and then it needs to be replaced.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's saying that a monk just purifies his mind, purifies his mind, purifies his mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: He doesn't go, oh, when will I?
[SPEAKER_01]: When will I not?
[SPEAKER_01]: Will I?
[SPEAKER_01]: Am I?
[SPEAKER_01]: He just keeps doing it, keeps doing it, keeps doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, when there's no more work to be done, he just obviously has to drop it and calm down.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then,
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you're asking if you're a sotāpanna, it means you're not.
[SPEAKER_01]: That doesn't mean what you're doing is wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: It just means you have to keep doing it more until basically you are unable to suffer amidst things that are making you suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, whether the whole world says you're a sotāpanna or you're not a sotāpanna, it doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: You went beyond suffering to that extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the reason why
[SPEAKER_01]: That person cannot sustain mindfulness, or rather mindfulness lapse, and then they suffer, because they lose perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's because the mind hasn't been developed enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you don't develop mind enough by getting more information, that can help.
[SPEAKER_01]: You develop the mind by sense restraint and upgrading the virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's the work.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why Buddha said, you know, if a monk keeps patimokkha, dwells restrained, moderate in eating, guards the sense doors, the mind becomes pliable, as a result of that training and taming.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what he thinks, then the mind will go where he thinks it, and he will be in control of it, not the other way around.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that person, obviously, doesn't want to be losing the perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because when they do, they're aware suffering arises and persists.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, if it were up to them, the mind would not lose the perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the mind doesn't listen to them.
[SPEAKER_01]: The mind loses perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why can the mind do that?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's because you still give in to the choices that enable mind to have control over you, not other way around.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the mind is not tamed.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whenever you can't sustain what you understood, or you're lapsing, or you're getting distracted, it's because you still keep choosing things rooted in greed, aversion and delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you're still acting out of distraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you need to upgrade the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or take them a bit more seriously or tightly and also guard the sense doors.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, eh... if you can't do that, then you have to accept the outcome, then the mind will get out of your control every now and then and you will suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that suffering will be worse than somebody who is not aware of the right context.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because ignorance is bliss to a degree.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why people do not see the suffering in sensuality and remain infatuated for the rest of their life.
[SPEAKER_01]: They pay the price later.
[SPEAKER_01]: Much worse price.
[SPEAKER_01]: But somebody who is aware and who loses perspective, that suffering will be felt worse, because they are aware of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, the compromise of not being sufficiently restrained, also then has more weight.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you realize, yeah, it is up to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there's no excuse.
[SPEAKER_01]: So if your mind is not in your control, it's because you haven't tamed it enough.